Like we do online shopping, we
shop from commerce websites, you shop,
you try the product, if it does
not meet your expectations
then what do you do, you return it.
Similarly, there
is a concept of free look period in insurance policies also, in which
if you buy a product and it is
not as per your expectations then you
can cancel it within the free look period.
So today we will talk about what is the free look period in your health
insurance and life insurance policy
and
when can you exercise the fill period,
what is the process of free look period and whether
you get a full refund or not.
Before starting the video, I would
like to introduce myself. My name is
Goodelink Go Chiku. I am a Certified
Financial Planner. I have been
associated with the insurance industry for the last 18 years
and every week I bring videos for you so that
my insurance bank journey becomes
easy and happy.
Before we start with you, a quick reminder, if
you haven't subscribed to our channel yet, do it.
So today you get the right information
and the right time. You will see a scanner on the screen. If
you scan this channel, you will
join us on every social media platform. Let's move on to the video.
Free look period and insurance. So,
free look, basically, as I can understand from the word itself, so
free look means you
can look at your policy carefully
because sometimes it is not possible.
When you are going to buy a policy, you should
look at the entire terms and conditions.
But even after buying the policy, if you
feel that you are not satisfied with it,
your expectations are not met. Here, you had
given some disclosures which have not come properly
in the policy, then you
can cancel the policy during the free look period. So, the meaning of free look is that there will be
no charges,
but again, there are some charges for the video and I will
talk about it in detail. Different
policies have different free
look periods. We will talk about that later. So,
first let's talk about health.  The
process of insurance period is first, what will be the start date for
your free look period?
You have taken the policy for health and assurance policy,
when you will receive the policy document,
not the policy issue date, from
where you have received your policy document,
even if it is in soft copy,
your free look period will be
counted from there, for how many days, for 15 days,
during those 15 days you
can check your policy completely, we have
also made a video in which we have talked about,
thanks to you look in your health and
assurance policy, if you take your health insurance
policy then you can also see
what all things you need to check whether
they are correct or not in the policy, secondly you can go
through the policy terms and conditions completely, whether the
product is as per your
expectation or not, if it is
not, then
you can cancel it within 15 days and you can
cancel it within the free look period, keep this in mind that
you will get this thing only for the first time when
you take a health insurance policy.  You
get the policy only when you are renewing it, you will
not get the free look period on time
or you are porting the policy, suppose
you have ported the policy from one insurer to another, the
free look period will
not be applicable there, you people are
asking a lot of questions, I have received a lot of queries
that I have done the porting, now I
want to cancel it under free look, but the
company is not letting me do it, it is saying that they will charge
20% or 25% because it is not a
new policy, portability is
not a fresh contract, hence
your free look period will not be applicable even on portability, suppose there is a
scenario where you have taken a claim during the free
look period, you have taken the claim on the policy locally, there is a
situation in which you had to take a claim, you have
taken the claim and the policy is still under free look
and you are cancelling it under free look, then the
company will refund your premium to you,
so the
risk premium that you have taken will be
refunded to you only after calculating it proportionately,
so now we will talk about  Actually
what is its process, how
can you exercise free look, so your
policy is good, you feel that what you
wanted is not there in the policy or you
want to cancel it, then there should be a
reason of cancellation because you will apply for free look, then
that reason of cancellation has to be
mentioned there, so you can do it
through email, you can email to
customer care of whichever insurance company
you have a policy, you can mail there that
this is the reason and I want to cancel my policy
or want to cancel it during the free look
period, so they will receive the mail and
after that they will do a knowledge,
they will also try to talk to you, they will
understand that why are you
cancelling, you have to give the date reason,
you got it and after that your refund will come
in 7 to 10 working days, so
basically I would like to tell you here that the
entire amount is not refunded,
brother are you  Friends, the charges are
small charges like your taxes, there will be
stambooti, ​​there will be administration charges
or your risk premium on
proportionate period, then that gets deducted and
you get your amount, so the process is
simple, there is not much TDS, but if you
want to exercise,
you can get your cancellation within the free look period by following this process.
Now we will talk about term
insurance policy, so in term and this
policy also it is necessary to
comfortably look at your policy
document, whether everything is correct or not,
read the terms and conditions, whether everything is correct
or not and accordingly you have just right,
you can exercise the free look period, so here
if there is a rule which is applicable,
you know all the rules of IIT, you have to
follow the insurance company, so in term
insurance or life and short term, a
free look period of 15 days is
given there, if you have taken the policy online or
through distance marketing, then a
period of 30 days is given, you can do it within 30 days  You
can cancel this policy and the
start date will be considered the same from the time you
received the policy. Now what happened earlier was that the
hard copy of the policy came and from there the
free look period was considered. Now
most of the companies do not give you hard
copies, they give you soft copy by post. There is
also Viso Green Initiative
of many companies which do not give you hard copies,
it is only on request. You
will receive the soft copy on your mail from there,
your free look period is counted from there, so the
15 days or 30 days application on
your policy will be counted from there. To cancel,
you will have to mail to customer care with
the reason of cancellation, why are you
wanting to cancel, they will tell you and similarly they might
talk to you tomorrow and
why are you wanting to do it, they will give you alternatives
that you can do it this way or that way. So, you know that
you had taken this insurance
policy after thinking carefully, so now what wait
why are you going to change your policy, so let the bill try to
convince you that you  Continue with
this right also because you had
taken the insurance for your family protection, so
why are you cancelling it now, but you
have this right to cancel the policy for free look,
so
within 7 to 10 days of receiving the mail, you get the cancellation amount
which is the refined amount, so
here also the same thing is applicable, whether you will
get the full amount or else you will not get the full amount,
your stamp charges which is stamp
duty, there are taxes, if you have got
any medical test done, normally
this happens in term, if you have got any medical test done, they will deduct the
cost of the medical test from
you and will refine your premium,
so the company has already levied the
cost of conducting the medical test on you,
so they will refund your premium by deducting it
and they can also deduct the risk premium of 40 minutes, so after
all this
your premium will be refunded to you, so if you
see the percentage, it will not be very much, that
means there will hardly be a small amount
in your total premium, which this  We will
come after doing everything in total, so this way we will talk about
free look in health in your hands and terminus,
any queries regarding this or if
you have had any experience or faced
any challenge while doing free look, then you
can tell us in the comment area, so that it will
help other people also, if you want to ask anything,
you can ask in the comment area, you
can send it to me on our email
ID and WhatsApp number, we will give right answer,
first quick reminder, if you have
not subscribed to our channel yet, do
subscribe, so that you
get the right information and the right time, see you
soon in the next video, be safe, take care, bye bye see
look period,
so before starting the video, I will tell you